Francis Bowler Keene Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Francis Bowler Keene Papers 1856-1975 (bulk 1877-1924)
MSS56804
Keene, Francis Bowler, 1856-1945
6,000 items
11 containers plus 1 oversize
4.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Diplomat, poet, and author. Diaries, correspondence, subject and writings files, and scrapbooks relating to Keene's career in the consular service and to his writings.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bacon, Robert, 1860-1919--Correspondence.; Bigelow, Poultney, 1855-1954--Correspondence.; Breckinridge, Henry, 1886-1960--Correspondence.; Carr, Wilbur J. (Wilbur John), 1870-1942--Correspondence.; Elliott, Eugene S.--Correspondence.; Guild, Curtis, 1860-1915--Correspondence.; Hackett, Elizabeth--Correspondence.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923--Correspondence.; Hay, John, 1838-1905--Correspondence.; Keane family.; Keene family.; Keene, David, 1820-1893--Correspondence.; Keene, Francis Bowler, 1856-1945.; Knox, Philander C. (Philander Chase), 1853-1921--Correspondence.; La Follette, Robert M. (Robert Marion), 1855-1925--Correspondence.; Loomis, Francis B. (Francis Butler), 1861-1948--Correspondence.; Rockhill, William Woodville, 1854-1914--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919--Correspondence.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937--Correspondence.; Spooner, John C. (John Coit), 1843-1919--Correspondence.; Stovall, Pleasant A., 1857-1935--Correspondence.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930--Correspondence.; Turner, Frederick Jackson, 1861-1932--Correspondence.; Watterson, Henry, 1840-1921--Correspondence.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927--Correspondence.; Woodbury, John--Correspondence.
Subjects
Consuls--Italy--Florence.; Consuls--Italy--Rome.; Consuls--Switzerland--Geneva.; Consuls--Switzerland--Zurich.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Italy.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Switzerland.; Golf.
Occupations
Authors.; Diplomats.; Poets.
Provenance
The papers of Francis Bowler Keene, diplomat, poet, and author, were given to the Library of Congress by Mrs. Emerin S. Chute and Carolyn W. Keene in 1976.
Transfers
Photographs and drawings have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the Francis Bowler Keene Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Francis Bowler Keene are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1856, Dec. 11 Born, Milwaukee, Wis.
1871 1875 Attended Racine College, Racine, Wis.
1880 Graduated, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1881 Engineer, Chicago, Milwaukee & St. Paul Railway
1893 Married Emerin Price Semple
1899 1902 Member, Wisconsin legislature
1903 1905 United States consular officer, Florence, Italy
1905 1915 United States consular officer, Geneva, Switzerland
1915 1917 United States consular officer, Zurich, Switzerland
1917 1924 United States counsel general, Rome, Italy
1923 Published Lyrics of the Links. London: C. Palmer
1924 Retired in Rome, Italy
1942 Returned to the United States
1945 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Francis Bowler Keene (1856-1945) span the years 1856-1975, with the bulk of the collection concentrated in the period 1877-1924. The collection is organized into eight series: Diary and Account Book, Personal Correspondence, Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, Subject File, Writings, Miscellany, and Oversize. Included are literary manuscripts, genealogical material, an autograph collection, and miscellaneous items such as printed matter, scrapbooks, presidential appointments, certificates, a chart, and memorial.
The collection focuses on Keene’s long career as a consular officer at Florence, Italy, Geneva and Zurich, Switzerland, and as consul general at Rome. The papers reflect Keene’s deep concern and conscientiousness in performing the duties of a consular officer. His mastery of French, German, and Italian was especially helpful during World War I, when many Americans were stranded in Europe and required the services of an experienced consular officer, particularly in Switzerland.
Keene’s papers relating to personal and family affairs also form a portion of the collection. His letters to his father, David Keene, while he attended Racine College in Wisconsin and Harvard University, reveal a close relationship between father and son. The letters later written to his wife and two daughters allow a brief insight into his immediate family relationships.
A few of the papers reflect on his contribution to the field of golf, for which he was known as “Laureate of the Links” in Europe as well as in America.
Keene’s principal correspondents include Robert Bacon, Poultney Bigelow, Henry Breckinridge, Wilbur J. Carr, Eugene S. Elliott, Curtis Guild, Elizabeth Hackett, Warren G. Harding, John Hay, Philander C. Knox, Robert M. La Follette, Francis B. Loomis, William Woodville Rockhill, Theodore Roosevelt, Elihu Root, John C. Spooner, Pleasant A. Stovall, William H. Taft, Frederick Jackson Turner, Henry Watterson, Leonard Wood, and John Woodbury.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eight series:
Diary and Account Book, 1876-1899
Personal Correspondence, 1886-1901
Family Correspondence, 1867-1975
General Correspondence, 1870-1945
Subject File, 1856-1939
Writings
Miscellany, 1892-1905
Oversize
Container List
- Diary and Account Book, 1876-1899 (Box 1)
  Diary notes and account book kept by Keene while he was guardian of his uncle, Edgar Keene.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Diary, 1876 (Box 1)
  - Account book for the estate of Edgar Keene, 1886-1901 (Box 1)
- Personal Correspondence, 1886-1901 (Box 1)
  Letterpress book containing impressions of holographic and typescript letters.
  Letters arranged chronologically.
  - 1886-1901 (Box 1)
- Family Correspondence, 1867-1975 (Box 1-4)
  Letters and related and attached material to and from family members.
  - Aug. 1867-Nov. 1886, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Jan. 1887-June 1893, (6 folders) (Box 2)
  - July 1893-Dec. 1916, (6 folders) (Box 3)
  - Jan. 1917-June, 1919, Jan. 1975, undated, (4 folders) (Box 4)
- General Correspondence, 1870-1945 (Box 4-6)
  Letters and attached and related material.
  - Sept. 1870-Mar. 1910, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Apr. 1910-Oct. 1915 (Box 5)
  - Nov. 1915-May 1945, undated, (9 folders) (Box 6)
- Subject File, 1856-1939 (Box 7)
  Genealogical material and autographs.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Autographs, 1918-1939, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Genealogy, 1856-1894 (Box 7)
- Writings (Box 7-10)
  Biographical sketches, poems, essays, short stories, and other writings.
  Arranged by title, topic, or type of material.
  - Lyrics of the Links (Box 7)
  - Our Marriage Vow, compiled by William N. Irish (Box 7)
  - Golf (Box 7)
  - Union Club, Rome, Italy (Box 7)
  - Wanderings of King Whim, newspaper column in Milwaukee Sentinel by Keene, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Biographical sketches (Box 8)
  - "Original Sayings of Emerin P. Semple Keene" (Box 8)
  - "Remarks on Washington's Birthday" (Box 8)
  - "Municipal and Political Verses" (Box 8)
  - "On Foothills of Parnassus" (Box 8)
  - "Metrical Letter to a Bridge Devotee and the Bookworms Lament" (Box 8)
  - "Angelina," by Paul Laurence Dunbar (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous verses, (3 folders); (4 folders) (Box 8, Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous short stories, (4 folders); 6 folders) (Box 9, Box 10)
  - "Anthology of Negro Humor" (Box 10)
- Miscellany, 1892-1905 (Box 10-11)
  Passports, printed matter, and scrapbooks.
  Arranged aphabetically by type of material.
  - Passports (Box 10)
  - Printed matter, (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 11)
    - 1892-1905 (Box 11)
    - 1895-1901 (Box 11)
    - undated (Box 11)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  Diplomas, appointments, certificates, charts, and memorials.
  - Appointments (Box OV1)
  - Certificates (Box OV1)
  - Chart (Box OV1)
  - Diplomas, Keene and Emerin Price Semple (Box OV1)
  - Memorial (Box OV1)